<!DOCTYPE webpage [ <!ENTITY eacute "&#233; "> <!ENTITY uuml "&#252; "> <!ENTITY nbsp " "> ]>
<webpage name="Andr&eacute;'s CBM IEEE488 interfaces">
  <author>
    <name>Andr&eacute; Fachat</name> 
<!--
    <yearstart>1999</yearstart>
    <yearend>1999</yearend>
-->
    <email>@EMAIL@</email>
    <homepage>@WEBROOT@</homepage>
  </author>
  <keywords>Commodore,IEEE488</keywords>
  <metadesc>IEEE488 interfaces for the Commdore 8-bit machines</metadesc>
  <overview>
On these pages you will find a number of IEEE-488 interfaces for Commodore
8-bit equipment as well as one for the PC printerport.
The IEEE-488 interface was used with the old CBM PET
computers to connect disk drives, printers, modems and more.
  </overview>
<!--
  <news>
    <item date="">
    </item>
  </news>
-->
  <itemlist name="IEEE 488">
    <description>The main bus that connects almost all of my CBM computers and devices
is the parallel IEEE488 bus, at least the version that CBM
implemented in the PET and CBM-II line of computers.
Not all of them are by me, but some are.
There is an <a href="http://www.funet.fi/pub/cbm/documents/projects/ieee-488/IEEE-488.txt">introduction</a> to the IEEE-488 bus by Ruud Baltissen.
    </description>
    <items>
      <subitem name="C64">The CBM IEEE488 interface for the C64 is used to connect the
C64 to the IEEE488 bus. I had my own (hand-drawn) schematics
here, but Wolfgang G&uuml;nther did it with a drawing program, and dumped
the ROM as well. Find the description in
<a href="http://www.funet.fi/pub/cbm/documents/projects/ieee-488/c64/">c64/</a>. A readme can be found in
<a href="http://www.funet.fi/pub/cbm/documents/projects/ieee-488/c64/README">ieee c64 readme</a>.
<br/>
The original software uses up some space in the $c*** area and completely
disabled the serial IEC bus. I wrote a modification to the C64 kernal
such that both busses can be used and the $c*** area is free. See the
<a href="../cbmhw/kernal/index.html">kernal pages</a>.</subitem>
      <subitem name="VIC20">Although I never owned a VIC20, I list this one here as well for completeness.
Wolfgang G&uuml;nther made the schematics of the original CBM IEEE488
interface for the VIC20 with a drawing program, and dumped
the ROM as well. Find the description in
<a href="http://www.funet.fi/pub/cbm/documents/projects/ieee-488/vic20">vic20/</a>.
</subitem>
      <subitem name="VC1541"> The now gone 64er magazin published a modification of the VC1541
to use an IEEE488 interface. It basically implements the IEEE488
interface of the 2031 drive, the IEEE488 sister drive to the VC1541.
Only the ROM code was modified such that only one of the two 8k ROM
chips had to be replaced by an EPROM.
Find the description in
<a href="http://www.funet.fi/pub/cbm/documents/projects/ieee-488/vc1541-ieee.tar.gz">vc1541-ieee.tar.gz</a>.
</subitem>
      <subitem name="PC-LPT">This interface is listed here because I use my PC as
a disk drive for my CBM equipment. Starting from ideas from
Ruud Baltissen (see
<a href="http://www.funet.fi/pub/cbm/documents/projects/ieee-488/pc-ieee.zip">pc-ieee.zip</a>)
I developed this interface for the PCs LPT port and wrote
the software (using some of VICE's disk emulation code).
Schematics, description and software (for Linux) can be found in
<a href="http://www.funet.fi/pub/cbm/documents/projects/ieee-488/lptiec-0.9.2.tar.gz">lptiec-0.9.2.tar.gz</a>.<br/>
Although the software is for Linux, it is written somewhat portably
in that no special kernel device or so is used. The program directly
interfaces the PC LPT hardware and should easily be ported.</subitem>
      <subitem name="IEEE488-&gt;IEC"> A friend of mine used the serial IEC bus
and not the IEEE488 bus to connect all his stuff. Unfortunately he also
used a CBM&nbsp;600 (aka B128). We designed a small device - a 6502
computer actually - that is put in between the two busses, converting the
parallel IEEE488 to the serial IEC bus. The schematics has longs since
been lost, so I reverse-engineered it from the last existing source file
for the ROM. Find the description in
<a href="http://www.funet.fi/pub/cbm/documents/projects/ieee-488/par2ser-1.tar.gz">par2ser-1.tar.gz</a>.</subitem>
    </items>
  </itemlist>
  <disclaimer name="Disclaimer">
All Copyrights are acknowledged.
There is no warranty of any kind attached to the information herein.
You may use this information for NON-COMMERCIAL use, unless where the
GNU Public License applies. Then its conditions hold.
  </disclaimer>
  <closing>
Contents last modified 15 June 2000
  </closing>
</webpage>
